<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A fraction in the assembly: or the synod in armes being a punctuall relation of their set meeting, upon the 25. of Aprill in this present year of our computation 1648 at a tavern in London, where the purposes of those reverend fathers, were piously discovered by themselves, in a mutuall conference by the strength of a dinner, in the truth of wine: their disagreement, upon the question: their falling out upon that; and how they were parted: with other mixtures of sad and merry accidents being all passages very remarkeable: and curious observations, which the author, as a generall well-wisher, delivers heer to the worlds view - and he hopes satisfaction.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84858</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2050</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E447_17</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204925</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864373</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864373</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116601</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84858)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116601)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 71:E447[17])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A fraction in the assembly: or the synod in armes being a punctuall relation of their set meeting, upon the 25. of Aprill in this present year of our computation 1648 at a tavern in London, where the purposes of those reverend fathers, were piously discovered by themselves, in a mutuall conference by the strength of a dinner, in the truth of wine: their disagreement, upon the question: their falling out upon that; and how they were parted: with other mixtures of sad and merry accidents being all passages very remarkeable: and curious observations, which the author, as a generall well-wisher, delivers heer to the worlds view - and he hopes satisfaction.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>14 [i.e. 16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare, 1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June 14th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116601:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:116601:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A FRACTION IN THE ASSEMBLY: OR THE SYNOD IN ARMES Being a punctuall Relation of their ſet meeting, upon the 25. of <hi>Aprill</hi> in this preſent year of our Computation 1648 at a tavern in LONDON, where the purpoſes of thoſe reverend Fathers, were piouſly diſcovered by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, in a mutuall conference by the ſtrength of a Din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and in the truth of wine: Their diſagreement, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the queſtion: their falling out upon that; and how they were parted: with other mixtures of ſad and merry ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents being all paſſages very remarkeable: and curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous obſervations, which the Author, as a generall well-wiſher, delivers heer to the worlds view- And he hopes ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>London Printed in the yeare, 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:116601:2"/>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:116601:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <l>AS once <hi>Olympian Jove:</hi> put <hi>Iuno</hi> by</l>
                  <l>And wiſe <hi>Minerva,</hi> Gave bold <hi>Mars</hi> the lye</l>
                  <l>Touching <hi>Troyes</hi> fate: when limping <hi>Uulcan</hi> ſcorus</l>
                  <l>To keepe heavens peace: and with ungratefull hornes</l>
                  <l>Butts at his freindly Rivall: Even ſuch odds</l>
                  <l>Tainted of late our ſublunary Gods</l>
                  <l>The ſacred Synod: which we mortalls call</l>
                  <l>The viols of Heavens wrath: O <hi>Troy:</hi> thy fall</l>
                  <l>Phaebus lamented: but in <hi>Englands</hi> dust</l>
                  <l>What hand writes pity, as if all were juſt</l>
                  <l>For patience has endurd: vengeance convince</l>
                  <l>Theſe of thir guilt and <hi>Charles</hi> that Godlike Prince</l>
                  <l>Let his white Truth prevaile: our ſtory cooles</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Lard ſeemes learning: and her fat rich fooles</l>
                  <l>Fed high with penſion dinners: Whoſe meere cloſe</l>
                  <l>Would burſt an Elephant: wele now ſpeake proſe,</l>
                  <l>Freinds what you ſee, beleeve, here is no lye</l>
                  <l>For when this chanc'd, the Authors ſelf was by</l>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Ray be not ſo angry Gentlemen; For that weighty misfortuns, whoſe Relations are to the publick, ſhould be knowne and conſidered, I deny not, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing otherwiſe, how ſhall men declare their modeſt ſorrowings in matters neerely concerning them, or ſtudy their prevention, In the future, If they be ignorant of them: All this without the rack: or hanging by the great toe, with the head downeward like A dancer of the Ropes; or any other inquiſition torture, is confeſt freely: but this is it that I ſay. why ſhould one poore beaſt, be forſt to carry the burthen for a whole Kingdome: becauſe Mrs. ſuch a one:<note place="margin">Shee is a Widdow.</note> the Miſtris of the Taverne where this famous accident befell, with her whole family, have taken the Covenant, or Oaths of ſecreſie with theſe fathers, Confeſſors; to hide it from honeſt men, and ſo keepe the world in this, like other things in ignorance and infidelity; muſt I therefore, weepe my ſelfe into a <hi>Tranſformation:</hi> Be made a new river, as ſome have been before mee, as you may read in the Hiſtory of <hi>Miobe</hi> and others, in Ovids unerring Chronicle of his Metamorphoſis or be turnd into a frogge, for over-laughing my ſelfe, When J have a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:116601:3"/>
mind to jeſt out my greifes: And all this becauſe, I only, had the fortune to be by — I ſay, there is no reaſon for it: no, there are more Aſſes in <hi>England</hi> beſides mee; let the matter be communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: that every <hi>Lucius</hi> taking up his owne load, we may Jogge on like contented Market-Women, or Citizens wives to their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try houſes, fairely, and eaſily together: to what uſe ſerve Ambages amongſt friends, or why ſhould the Author with tedious Apologies Cuffe his ſtory into teares; becauſe he thruſts her back, and reſtraines her appearing, Even now, when by all viſible ſignes, ſhe hath A mighty mind to diſcover her ſelfe, take it therefore amongſt you, which in few words befell thus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vpon St. Markes day the</hi> 25. <hi>of Aprill the holines whereof is much envied by our Libertines of England, becauſe the ſuperſtitious Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans, obſerve it: halfe a dozen of our Synodicall Presbytery, peiced with juſt as many Independants, to make up the number, though of ſeverall colours, had a mind to condogge together.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Their meeting was at a Tavern in <hi>London,</hi> not a ſtrecht mile from the Old Exchange: which to cover the Nakedneſſe of a prime Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, the daughter of the houſe, and 'tis thought the loadſtone of that ſociety, ſhall for the preſent be nameleſſe.</p>
            <p>After an humble Thankſgiving, for their arrivall at <hi>terra florida</hi> And that being ſuch, who by ſins of an unrecoverable miſcreancy, had tempted Heaven and Earth to deſtroy them, yet, the ſtones in the ſtreets, had not riſen up againſt them, either to breake their ſhins or their Necks in that their pilgrimage, concluding with an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, what providence that ſhould be that ſtill continu'd to protect them: Impenitent ſinners, they ſeated themſelves at a large round Table in a very faire Roome, and calling for fine <hi>Angelica</hi> which ſhall be her name here, after a briefe catachizing touching the ſtate of her virginity, and how the pulſe of her Concupiſcences did beate, whereof ſhe was much comforted to heare them tell her, all fleſh was guilty, ſhe received from them a bleſſing upon the lip, and they from her faire hand, the cup of Salutation, which that pretty Leman preſenting with wine and ſugar, they did her reaſon firſt, and then toſt it of freely one to another.</p>
            <p>The <hi>joyning</hi> of two rounds together, engendred a diſcourſe deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by a Doctor, in theſe words following, Brethren, we are heer <hi>condo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>d together: As it were, to peck up a few Crummes of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:116601:3"/>
from this our mutuall enjoying one of another: in the plenty of the Creature, which we preſently expect, cal'd Meat, Wine, and Woemen: Renowned Subjects of the three firſt miracles: of theſe, we may feed till we burſt againe, for our purſes are full, the people our friends, And therefore the Houſe is likewiſe ours, while wee, whom the prophane of the Land call evill ſpirits, ſhall pleaſe to poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe it, But firſt, let us adviſe, and unſcruple our ſoules, leaſt any thing by chance, ſhould lie pinching us in that tender place, to the hurt of our preſent or future tranquillities: If any of you doubt, let him only queſtion, And be reſolved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The motion was applauded, and thus trod upon the very heele by another, then are we quoth hee, the moſt miſerable of all men, if <hi>vox populi,</hi> carrie it's old credit, for that cals us the Incendiaries of the Nation: It ſaies, that weekly preaching have advanced Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Murder, Theft, Confuſion, and every evill worke: That we have brought contempt upon the Ghoſpell; That outwardly we conteſt as oppoſits, but ſecretly are agreed to nouriſh diviſions ſo long, like the <hi>Scotts,</hi> wee have gathered all buſineſſe into our diſcuſſing, that we may Judge and determine all things as chiefe moderators in matters of conſcience, and ſo, by degrees, ſteale the Soveraignty from King and People, and Plant it in our ſelves, the Clergy.</p>
            <p>That neither wee, nor any Authorized by us, or lawfull Miniſters, becauſe we have forfited our calling by the double breach of thoſe two Oathes, Alleageance and Supremacy, which bound us to the King: who when he hath vanquiſht his toiles, will, they ſay, have us baited in Beares-skins, for playing to much the Foxes, as firſt to Drill him into a ſnare; And then ſet Doggs to worry him; not thoſe of a Generous kind, but mangy Mungrell Currs, cald <hi>Mildmay, Martin, Haman,</hi> and our ſelves, to whom they ſay, the Rogue laſt nam'd is only Turn-key; but we his Jailours, that may free him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly, if we would but ſweeten the polluted Aire with pure Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity. And from wounded hearts in penitentiall Pulpits, Ingemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate to Heaven, and men, our hearty ſorrowings for the high Crime, of our Soveraigne Lords unjuſt and violent Captivity, firſt cauſ'd by us, and now contrived by our connivences; in fine that all our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Prayers, are abhominations, becauſe our hands, they ſay are full of blood, neither can they heare our preaching, if they would, the Keyes of — keep ſuch a noiſe and ratling at our Girdles, all
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:116601:4"/>
which render us worſe then <hi>Baals</hi> Prieſts, or the 600. falſe Prophets that propheſied lies, and perſecuted the good men of God. Theſe Imputations that bold <hi>Vox Populi</hi> that preſumes to call Infinit thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of Men,<note place="margin">The Chair mans An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer is all their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions.</note> Women, and Children, nay, our owne Conſciences forſooth, for Witneſſes; he ſweares are no ſlanders, but bleeding truths, which ſo wounds my thoughts, and conſumes me in this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry minute, that if your <hi>Sack</hi> here were not perfect <hi>Charinco,</hi> and the ſmell of our approaching Dinner reſtorative. I ſhould verily faint, and drop out of this Land of the living, and your Good Companies which would much greiue mee; to grope out uncertaine chances in another world, where tis ten to one, they ſerve not God after our manner; ſo, he ſipt off his Cup: was pledgd round, and thus ſatisfied by the Chaire-man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Brother:</hi> we muſt ſute the behaviour of our Actions to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, or humor of their cauſes, which command ours at this time, to obſerve the poſture they now ſtand at: The people indeed ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime, I ſay their cries are juſt, for by us, a Cloud is brought upon their Lawes, Liberties, Eſtates, nay perſons and all this by preaching, yet if this preſent momentary ill, conduces to their future good e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally: who ſhould theſe beetles thank, but us; Bitches have clogs: which we take off, to make them happy, if the ſilly Irrationall Cattell could but underſtand it, however, wee, that know it neceſſary are bound to practiſe it, for all their goods.</p>
            <p>This Generation muſt ſuffer, for the ſins of thoſe paſt, and all that are to Come: The next by our endeavors, ſhall ſhine againe, with a Government ſo pure, and like heaven, that Angels ſhall ſeeme to be beguild, and love to live, at leaſt converſe with men as formerly, miſtake mee not, I meane with us heere in <hi>England:</hi> As for the <hi>Scotts,</hi> lately our Brethren, they are revolting poore Rogues, not worthy now, nor ever able to entertaine ſuch Gueſts: Let not theſe Nitts diſquiet you Mr.—to make you throw of the Dublet of your firſt reſolutions, If a rampant lowſe, or two, chance to trouble you, yet never unbutton for the matter, only tell me where they bite, ile helpe you to a remover ſtrait: come heers the Man, he was thank'd, pledgd, and ſhould have beene encountred with a reply, but as the word was ſallying out of the Reſpondents Lips: it was forſt to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coile by a whole file of Diſhes, which juſt then preſented upon them, The falling on was furious; they came ſuddenly to pell mell, And ſlaſht it without mercy.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:116601:4"/>You will aske paradventure, how I came to know all this; Ile tell you: A freind and <hi>I</hi> had agreed over night to meet at that very Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verne about 10 this morning, <hi>I</hi> kept my appointment, but my freind, as the faſhion is, failed me. <hi>I</hi> with a pinte of the pureſt before me, ſell a ſleepe, and was, it ſeemes, aſwell forgot by the houſe as my ſelfe, till the entrance of ſo many, and ſo neere me, with the ſhuffling of leggs and feet, ſtarted me in ſuch a fright, as had there been a chim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney in the roome, <hi>I</hi> had certainely appeared at the top in a trice, and rather crept out that way, to ſhift for my ſelfe, then ſtood to the mercy of that Corporall, and his Squadron, for ſo <hi>I</hi> ſtrongly fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied theſe to be, that came to ſearch for malignants; of which outlaw'd family, my owne a King-heart told me verily, that <hi>I</hi> was a forlorne Brother; well, the Divill a Chimney was there, or a hole bigg e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, for Tom Thumbe to have hid himſelfe in; there was no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy: <hi>I</hi> compoſed my fears the beſt J could, &amp; ſetled my ſelfe, to li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten their ſitting diſcourſe, but eſpecially the ſight of them thorough a clift in the wainſcot, which only divided us, for t'was in the next a roome, ſo confirmed mee; that <hi>I</hi> drove care away to kill catts, and ſat prancking it upon my bench, as proudely, as St. <hi>George</hi> did upon his Beaſt, after he had killed the Dragon. Haveing given you this ſatisfaction, you are bound in conſcience to read on, and beleeve every word as followeth. Wee left them at dinner at the Tables end, ſat the fatt Miſtris of the Houſe, with a face appearing like a full Moone; by whome there ſhined her daughter, the faire <hi>Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lica,</hi> whoſe brightneſſe ſo ſtellified the roome, that thoſe elders could doe nothing elſe for a while, but drinke, and dart glances, feathered with wanton language at her, which ſhe retorted like a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother <hi>Venus,</hi> till her Tongue travel'd tantivie, and more then a <hi>Canterbury</hi> pace, and never Stopt till Mr. — Aſſaulted the Chaireman, whoſe place the Miſtris had borrowed very freſhly with ſome fragments of the firſt queſtion.</p>
            <p>That although what he had uttered, was profound and undenia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, yet he was ſtill to ſeeke in two maine particulars; firſt of the Church differences which he ever held reall, till then, next touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the King: who being a Juſt: Good: Gratious: Mild: Merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: Magnanimous: Valiant: Pious: Wiſe Prince: in his opinion he deſerved Nobler uſage, and to be at liberty: The Doctor replied tis true; you have not flattered him in all this Glorious Charecter
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:116601:5"/>
for, tis his due; which is Attribute we owe to all: nay, the very Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbe commands it for the Devill, yet to the King we muſt deny, this, under the Roſe here, weel give it him, amongſt our ſelves, but not publikely, for know: The government by Kings, and that wee aime at, which is to exalt the Church above it, are incompatible: If wee, ſubmitting to the equity you ſpeak of, which pleads hard for the King: ſhould replant him, you ſhould quickly perceive, what wild fruits that fooliſh Honeſty would bring forth: The awfull of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Biſhops would certainly floriſh again; Then pray what would become of vs: marry, Ile tell ye — if we ſcap'd hanging, even preſently be farted out of the Land, perhaps into that Jakes of <hi>Scotland,</hi> like ſome griping diſeaſe among the Gutts, or the wind Collick of the Kingdome: which they begin already to call Vs: No if we wiſh our owne utility, and the Churches Honor, we muſt heap <hi>Pelion</hi> upon <hi>Oſſa,</hi> raiſe ſuch a mount of ſcandals in the Kings way, as may bar his returne for ever, as being too high for all his patience or vindications, to climbe over, for example. Ther's <hi>Anthony Mild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>may,</hi> a dear Proſelyt of ours. I can never call thee Rogue to mind, but me thinks, I wiſh my hands were ſtroaking his zealous heart, and chaſing it into new deſignes for us: This precious villaine, in a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to that Saint his Brother, ſome call him Serpent, becauſe he ſtings the King that cheriſht him: I confeſſe an offence that would damme him, were he not a Son of the Cauſe, and we his defenders, charge his Majeſty with ſeverall expreſsions in diſcourſe, which he cals Tyrannies, and Inveighing againſt him, with the extreameſt tart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of a depraved Pen expoſes him to a malevolent cenſure, now we perceiving how the ſlave betraid his Maſter, by poiſoning the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence of his language, and meaning with wreſted conſtructions of his owne, which we well knew were falſe; Though we Admir'd the fellowes Impudency, yet we cheriſht his Information for the reaſon aforeſaid: and made ſpeciall uſes of it, to our owne eternall advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, as we Imagine, and the Kings finall detriment: This which we hold far better, then an Act of oblivion or Indemnity, meets your feares of after queſtionings, and calls them Triviall.</p>
            <p>Touching your ſecond doubt of our pretended Church differences Brethren, that the condition of ſtate Affaires is ſometimes ſuch as forces us, that manage them, to a <hi>deceptio viſus,</hi> A piece of <hi>Hocus,</hi> to benight mens Eyes at noone, and falſifie their object for their ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:116601:5"/>
We preſent ſomethings to the publick view juſt as they are, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers not ſo, but as they ſeeme to be by our direction: we are not to ſentence any evill deſperate, whoſe remedy is in our ſelves, one famous trick of pure conveyance carried it, for we, the Synod firſt, and then the Parliament, pretended to divide, we preached, writ, diſgraced one another to the uttermoſt, which wanted no ſucceſſe, for the ſilly people, juſt as we imagin d, couzen'd with empty face of anger, ran preſently to ſides, and quickly wound the quarrell up to ſuch a height, as to avoid the cruſhing of a party when the weight ſhould fall, the continuance of an Army was reſolved upon, and ſo by their own miſ-priſions, counted neceſſary, which fitted our deſires juſt: This plot, thus wiſely laid, was likewiſe fortunate, for being thus ſeemingly oppoſite, we can open our pack by turnes, now the <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> then the <hi>Independent,</hi> and paſſe our wares at what price wee pleaſe upon the ſhallow world, which receives all our brocage, [as ſome diſparage it] it the ſecond hand, paying truly the deare rates of many thanks, and Reverence, not from any skill of their owne to judge, but as wee adorne it, with a gloſſe, and praiſe it.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee, thoſe our Sons of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Obſerve the confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</note> and <hi>London</hi> obey our contrivings: Our ſervants <hi>Fairfax,</hi> and <hi>Cromwell,</hi> like <hi>Eſau</hi> and <hi>Nimrod,</hi> ſmell ſtrongly of the field, and ſavor rank of the blood we command them to ſpill in hunting: and laſtly, wee, the Sages of <hi>Europe,</hi> and <hi>Englands</hi> Reverendiſſimoes, do keepe unity, as well as we can, and concord in a Golden band, <hi>I</hi> meane amongſt our ſelves being alwaies careful that neither of our parties outweigh the other, but both to lye ſo hard upon the King and his followers, that wee wonder, by what virtue or miracle they live.</p>
            <p>This, I have told you, is the very heart of the affaire, which theſe dotterells of the Laity are not to ſearch into, but you the Sons of <hi>Eli,</hi> and my deare <hi>Iockey's</hi> muſt dive into the bottome of this or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other ſecret, wherein my art can pleaſure you.</p>
            <p>After this Oration, he watered his dry pallate with a ſhower of White wine, to which he was very devoutly affected, and liquored his tongue to make it fruitfull for more flowers of <hi>Rhetoricke:</hi> That done, he demanded their opinion of what he had offered one, whoſe hands I marked were no unprofitable Servants to his ſtomack for in the interim of this long parley they had ſtored the Magazine of his belly with a moneths proviſion at leaſt, for feare of a famine from <hi>Kent</hi> and other Mutinous Counties, entreated the Chaire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:116601:6"/>
to excuſe them, foraſmuch as they had not been at leiſure to hearken to his Tale, which notwithſtanding, they were confident, was all true from the beginning, to the end of the laſt ſyllable: it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no more poſſible for him to erre, then the Popes holineſſe: To whoſe two Chaires, Infallibility, was equally annexed in aſſurance whereof, A black fellow, very like Mr. <hi>Marſhall,</hi> and ſure <hi>I</hi> think t'was he, taking up a weighty Boll, brim-full of <hi>Sack,</hi> offered to drink to any man in the Company that would pledge him, and be of his opinion; his challenge was received immediatly by another: what replied a third, that they ſay, ſeldome ſpake a true word, but in his Drink, is not this in the Devills name, a trick of the beaſt, to tell the people of a <hi>Cock</hi> and a <hi>Bull,</hi> and bind them to beleeve all the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries in <hi>Chawcer</hi> for Articles of Faith: pray what's this, but <hi>Implicita fides:</hi> the very bumbaſte father of <hi>Ignorance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Brother,</hi> anſwerd the Chaire-man, That ignorance you deſpiſe ſo much, is, being rightly conceived, the true and ſober parent, not only of devotion towards Heaven, but of reverence to us: of which laſt Jewell it behoves us to have a more tender care, then of the other: Oracles were admir'd of old, becauſe, dark and ſtupendious, let a Riddle be once expounded, and every fool will tread upon it: I tell you againe, they muſt not be able to fathom our depth, tis ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for them, to practiſe obedience, and for us, to embrace the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of our witty forefathers of the laſt <hi>Trent Councell,</hi> who when they added new, and ſtrange Articles, all contradiction to thoſe, was death, for a crime cald by them, <hi>Haereſy;</hi> and now by us Felo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,<note place="margin">Marke this Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which is true.</note> eſpecially about the <hi>Ius Divinum,</hi> of our Presbyterian Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, never known till <hi>Calvin,</hi> by whom to ſpeak Truth, it was firſt broached, to get the man a name, and pleaſe the humorous pallate of the hare braind people.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oderant ſi metuunt,</hi> Let them hate me ſo they feare me, was the Motto of a Tyrant,<note place="margin">A Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Mot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, allowd by the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod.</note> and yet in my judgement a ſentence more Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, then any of <hi>Catoes:</hi> we muſt compell the vulgar Adoration to us, As the Divell does the Indians, Appeare in mild ſhapes to thoſe that love us, or ſubmit willingly, but be formidable to the reſt: you ſee how theſe Goats deſert us daily, &amp; are not their revolts ſufficient to excuſe our cruelty, nay though we damn'd them after death — O how I am taken with your grave politicks, — &amp; ſtand amazed at the profound myſterie of Propheſies: Machiavell crie <hi>I,</hi> was a ſprightly Gentleman, within <hi>Duce Ace,</hi> as wiſe as the Devill, if not wiſer: and Mother <hi>Shipton,</hi> As vaſt in her divinations, and as
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:116601:6"/>
Authentick an Author as any <hi>Sybill</hi> of them all: he drank to em, expecting an Applauſe—but it would not ſerve his turne, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing holyday as I told you, the Wine had kindled Bonefires in their braines, they valued neither him, nor his Chaire, and his language had ſo offended one, that he told him plainly he took him for <hi>Bara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas,</hi> The Father of Inſurrections, not halfe ſo honeſt as a Brewers Clark, whoſe falſe Tally was alwaies ſworn to Cozen either the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter or his Cuſtomers, The Prolocutor, who to my thinking, rav'd, hearing this, and fearing worſe: cald all the Godly of both parties to ſide with him, if he were affronted further by that—ly—ing Raſcall, I think he would have ſaid, but the lye was returned into his Throat, before he could get out the reſt, and had almoſt choaked him, being rammed downe by three great Teeth of his owne, which were driven from their Palliſadoe, by an aſſault and battery.</p>
            <p>He that gave this blow, I marked to be a man, whoſe face was ſo dyed in the Grain of Claret, that his plump Cheeks lookd for all the World, like a couple of flowing Wine-bagges, which in a moment were emptied, by a quick reſponſe from the Chaire-man, that with a caſt of his Office, hit him ſo home and hardily, as drew the Vintage in his face through the Spigot of his Noſe, and laid him flat upon the ground, like a bunch of Grapes new preſt.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Patroclus</hi> had an <hi>Ajax,</hi> that beſtird him, who mowed downe the Chaireman at one ſwing with a pottle Pot, All hands were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerciſ'd in a moment, And by a rare method or keeping due time betwixt feet and fiſts, No man could take them for any other then profeſt dancers, that were notably skilfull in obſerving the <hi>Decorum</hi> of A brawle: The fray was ſilent, ſharp, and ſhort, for the houſe, cheifly <hi>Angelica,</hi> came running up, and parted them: They re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnd to their ſeats: ſmil'd, at the Captiouſneſſe of great ſpirits, and cald for a Gallon of <hi>Nepenthe,</hi> a reconciling Drink, which they ſwallowed liberally, and were friends: The next Act was voiding the Table of all things, but a faire Cloth, a miraculous great Pie, plenty of wine to cleanſe their mouths, and Tobacco to foule them againe.</p>
            <p>Their wits went now a wool-gathering, from Learning the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend wagges, would needs grow wanton with a peice of divina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, What quoth one, <hi>if theſe Divells in</hi> Kent <hi>and</hi> Eſſex, <hi>ſhould get the better of our Saints in the Army, and ſo demand the Angells, in our two Houſes: And then thoſe ſpirits of the middle Region, the Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doners, in whoſe power I confeſſe it lies to diſpatch the buſineſſe in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:116601:7"/>
few houres, ſhould deliver them up, What would then become of us all;</hi> — The chaire-man whoſe cuſtome it was to fall upon the kernell of the buſineſſe, for you ſee, he opened the ſhells as faſt, as any <hi>Weſell</hi> can crack nuts,<note place="margin">New Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</note> replyed inſtantly, <hi>That all would prove indifferently well, for let it raine Doggs, and Cats, we, ſaid he, will recover our old ſanctified plantation, in deſpight of them, our ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limer Saints: As</hi> Lenthall, Martin, Mildmay, <hi>and the reſt ſhall ſtep aſide into their ſeverall ports in Neighbour Nations, where they may unite the forces of Treaſure, and craft, of both which they have a large ſtock, as occaſion ſhall invite them, to toſſe new balls and make</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>and <hi>wilde by the fire of another new Warre,</hi> This would be meritori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous you know.</p>
            <p>All in Good time, went on the <hi>Objector,</hi> If wee as you ſay, are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to cry, <hi>noli me tangere,</hi> when danger is ready to faſten, yet what will become of the frie, that have borne up our weake flights, upon the ſtrength, and reach of their long winged votes, and have all this while ſided with us, for theſe not being of the cabinet Counſell, will 'tis like, know nothing of the bogge, till they beſt fled in it.</p>
            <p>They are good for nothing elſe, anſwered the Chaireman, but to be regarded, like Bills, and Bonds out of date, bundled up together for waſt papers, and reſerved only for <hi>poſterior</hi> uſes, — As they have voted with us, from the beginning without judgement, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt conſcience, ſo let them eene be hanged for us at laſt, Thats all <hi>I</hi> care.</p>
            <p>Now you ſpeake of that, ſaid another, <hi>I</hi> am within an Inch of death with laughing: when <hi>I</hi> but think of that great Animall <hi>Pem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brook,</hi> a fellow that appears amongſt the Lords in the upper houſe as the Devill did in Heaven, in a ſhuffling way, having indeede, no priviledge to be found in any place, where wit ſhould dwell, — Lord, what a Legacy of non-ſence, that <hi>Buffoone,</hi> will bequeath to the jeering Malignants when they are throug'd together to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold him, as he ſtands upon his degrees, for he hath lately beene at <hi>Oxford</hi> ye know, to preach his owne funerall ſermon at ſome ſele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted Gallowes, for tis verily thought, that party, if they can but fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger him, wil never honour ſuch a keckſhaw with the ſolemnity of a Scaffold, This Earle ſayes another, ſhould be alwayes thrown upon Tumults to pacifie them, for let him talke what he liſt to diſpleaſe the people, hees ſure, they cannot all knock out his braines, for theſe not only he, but all the reſt of the Peers, have delivered up to the ſingle cuſtody of <hi>Viſcount Say,</hi> a crafty Merchant that hath
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:116601:7"/>
ſealed them up from all mens uſes, but his owne, which makes their Honors ſit with empty Noddles, from whence they ſay, The higher Houſe is called an Hoſpitall of fools, and in ſubjection to the lower who for this very reaſon are to be their Guardians.</p>
            <p>To this point they came; neither did theſe mountains of diſcourſe want their vallies, into which I will not trouble your diſcent, let it ſuffice us over looking many inferiour paſſages of the day to walke on ſtill keeping the higher ground till we arrive at Eleaven at night, which finiſhes the tragedy, and diſmiſſes the ſpectators.</p>
            <p>Eleaven was the houre, till which time, though <hi>I</hi> had not eat a bit, yet <hi>I</hi> was not faſting: <hi>I</hi> confeſſe <hi>I</hi> fed not, like other men at the mouth, but by the eye, and eare aboundantly my noſe too, came in for a ſhare, which thruſting out of my Caſement, ſnuft up the hot ſteam of their broath and baKte meat, which nouriſht me ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly.</p>
            <p>They were now high flown: <hi>Bacchus</hi> had crown'd all their temples with vermillion: his owne colours which are commonly purchaſed at a drunken rate, and looking thorough their owne eyes, now turn'd into multiplying Glaſſes, they ſtrongly fancied the huge pie before them to be full as big as <hi>London</hi> within the walls, this once falling into apprehenſions already diſtemperd: they ſtept into a higher de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of madneſſe,<note place="margin">The won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull power of drinke,</note> for an <hi>Independant</hi> ſtarted up and ſwore it was <hi>London</hi> it ſelfe, ſhewing the Armes, which ſaid he, you may behold blazon'd here upon one of her gates [he ment the Lid, where indeed they were Gallantly flouriſhed] and therefore I &amp; my companions, embracing the opportunity, will now beſeige, and take it, for this we know is the maine deſigne of the Army, and all the well-affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed party.</p>
            <p>They grew from words to Action, and prepar'd in earneſt, ſome to deſtroy, others to defend it: The batterie was feirce, many a ſadd blow was diſcharged at the Pie that fell heavily upon one face or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in a word, the Independent party prevaild, and the Chaire-man their Leader, beating downe the walls by force of Armes, the Cart of his ſtomack was the firſt that wheeld in, whereof himſelfe being Charioteer and Guide, he bore down all before him, and did a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible execution with his owne hand.</p>
            <p>The fortifications being quite leveld, profeſt friends fell to the plunder, like Enemies; never did poore Citizens ſuffer perſecution: and devouring with ſo much ſtrange patience, not a Groane, nor ſigh, it ſeemes remembring their faults againſt the King they ſilently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed all theſe puniſhments juſt, well, extreames cannot laſt allwaies,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:116601:8"/>
the Conqueror tyr'd with the labour of his own cruelty,<note place="margin">This was don by the Cook-maid and A Drawer as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves told me ſince, when they perceivd I knew the matter.</note> was willing to pardon the miſerable ſurviving relicks, which beginning to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, they found them to be a Cluſter of Froggs, well doeſt and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned: The men were amazd, and the Woemen ſcrietched like Owles to ſee the Metamorphoſis, and kneeling downe in a cold per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexity, they confeſt themſelves to thoſe Ghaſtly Fathers, in Termes Auricular, that as they never hoped to ſee Heaven, it was as ſweet a Woodcock pie, as ever kiſt the Lipps of a moderne Apoſtle: feare became fury: They gave all Pies they ſaid to the Divell, it was a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty they look'd after, whoſe Inhabitants conquered by them, were firſt turnd into Frogs, by Art Magick, and now at the beſt, made but Woodcocks by the Sorſereſſes.</p>
            <p>Two only of the Twelve perſwaded Peace, and in Scripture phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes but could not be heard, for all ſpirit of meekneſſe bad forſaken them, yet being conſcious in themſelves, that they all had a ſmacke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in Nicromancy, which they ſtudied more then divinity, they fell into a ſuſpition, that ſome one among them, had done this, to put a trick upon the reſt; but the Chaire-man, that ſnorted like <hi>Bucepha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, Alexanders horſe,</hi> in whom the fire of the firſt diſdaine was freſhly kindled, being before but rak'd up in a diſſembled pacificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, would needs preſſe the buſineſſe in tempeſtuous language upon him, that had firſt ſtricken him, who likewiſe grudging at him with a fervent emulation thus retorted: that rather he himſelfe was the man, for who knew not him to be alwayes drawing lines of infernall communication, ſpending moſt of his time in familiar conference with a certaine Divel, whoſe name he had forgot, finally, he Affirm'd him to be one that ſurmounted <hi>Fauſtus</hi> in Magick, and could make babies of thoſe two learned Friers,<note place="margin">A terrible blow.</note> 
               <hi>Bacon,</hi> and <hi>Bungey.</hi> The brazen head had ſpoke his laſt, for at this word the War broke out againe; one Cuffe from the Chaire upon the others Right Eare, made his head face quite about to the left ſhoulder, without hope, ever to ſee right forwards againe: This mortall chance engaged all the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, who fell aboord, and battered one another without mercy: It ſeemd to raine Cloaks and Hatts,<note place="margin">The maine battell.</note> while Ruffs, bands, and Caſſocks, were diſmembred like the Frogs they had eaten, and flew up and downe as if they had been alive.</p>
            <p>One there was amongſt the reſt, that had entertain'd the Time and Company, with a long diſcourſe in praiſe of <hi>Reebahs</hi> ſober Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacy to his Sons, whoſe very neer Kinſman he proved himſelfe to be, at the diſtance only of 2019. Generations, which he aſſur'd them was
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:116601:8"/>
all, and all the reaſon he knew, why that language of Hebrew ſeemd to him more naturall then this of his own mother Tongue: beeing as he offered to make it appeare, deſcended, <hi>ab originali,</hi> from the <hi>Iewes,</hi> and drawing his pedigree in ſtraight line, from <hi>Caiphas</hi> his Chamber keeper: <hi>Malchas</hi> told the wench that made fires in the high Prieſts Hall, the very fame, that made <hi>Peter</hi> deny his Maſter,<note place="margin">He had Records to witneſſe it.</note> which two he proteſted were Married together: This Gallant, by way of pure imitation would drink no Wine, but had ſo drownd himſelfe in a River of <hi>Ale,</hi> as getting into the middle of the roome, and ſtaring upon that wild crew, with Goggle-eyes, he ſtood there fixt, as if ſome body had turnd him into A Pillar of Malt, never to be removed, till the furious Chaire-man by the triall of Feet and Fiſts, quickly found him to be a dirty Moveable, and kickt him out of the roome.</p>
            <p>Another that waited his opportunity, and ſeemd to pitty the Damſell becauſe he ſaw her in diſmay, led her meekly into a darke Cloſer in a corner of the roome, where clinging about her like jvy, he recoverd her by the virtue of frication, reclaimd her Haggard ſmiles, and made her feelingly merry: her abſence was quickly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented by one, that loved her dearly, who ungrappling from a Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell that had boorded him, gave them Chaſe by the ſent, and found that <hi>Rabbin</hi> pluming his pullet inſtead of a <hi>Partridge,</hi> confounded with Jelouſie he bellowd out a rape, untwined their embraces, and flew upon his Rivall like a Cat A-mountaine, his roaring compelled the reſt to take notice of him, and being all in charity with the Nymph, which I beleeve was none of <hi>Dianaes,</hi> they took a minutes truce, and ran to her reſcue, where they diſcovered their Pigeon all to be ruffled, and the two enraged Combatants upon the Ground: clawing one another like a couple of Curry-combes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> am not able to expreſſe the Chaire mans fury, whoſe peculiar dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſhe was, his anger groand, and he foamd at the mouth, and grew ſo inſolent that he invaded freind and foe; at that inſtant high mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night appeared amongſt them an old man or a little fellow not ſo tall as himſelfe by the head, for he wanted one, <hi>I</hi> would faine have ſeene his face but could not for the reaſons aforeſaid, yet <hi>I</hi> think it was the Martyr <hi>Land,</hi> his hands arm'd with whips; ſcourged that Martiall Crew into admirable diſcipline, and it ſeemes, his blowes ſmarted, for they friskt up and downe the roome like Morris dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:116601:9"/>
The firſt that fled in this dreadfull viſion, was <hi>Angelica, who running downe ſtaires fell flat upon her face, at the bottome of them with her Traine, ſmock and all about her eares, and expoſing a paire of lovely buttocks, to the view, lay So as if ſhe had been dead by their diſpaires, two Doctors followed her at the heeles; one fell upon her right, the other upon her left hanch, which being white, pubble, and ſweet, they kiſt them cloſe with their cheeke, and fell faſt aſleepe, The Chaireman himſelfe came laſt, which flying from his tormentor, tript likewiſe upon the Virgin, and ran his noſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly into her Moon-ſhine,</hi> Thoſe Heroes <hi>above terribly affrighted and tyrannically laſht, dropt downe ſuddenly into a Trance, and all was ſilent. The Miſtris had gotten her load and ſate below with eyes faſt lock'd, the Servants had likewiſe their ſhares, and preſented themſelves the true family of night, upon whom</hi> Morpheus <hi>had caſt the charme of a leaden ſlumber.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I, that was not with out my ſhiverings at this midnight ſpectacle, and not delighting in ſuch cruelty graſped the occaſion: opened my doore ſoftly and ſtept upon the ſtage, where I ſaw ſuch wonders acted: It was pav'd with cloakes, the candles, which ſignified that that ſpirit was not evil never went out, but gided me to ſeveral wines which well brew'd with ſugar, <hi>I</hi> powred downe plentifully. <hi>I</hi> ſeizd upon a light and ſaw how Ruffs, Coats, cloaks and beards lay ſtrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up and downe, as thick as ruſhes: ſacriledge, I rememberd to be a ſinne, and therefore touched none of thoſe babiloniſh gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, leaſt I ſhould ſeeme to be guilty of it and rob their Church, but glided gently downe, and could hardly bridle my laughter, to ſee how thoſe Doctors lay like Church leeches, ſucking at the breech of the body politique, and certainly they hit upon the right veine, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially he in the midſt that had the beſt ſhare by ods, for ſhe had e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacuated as freely in his face, as if he had been newly giving her a Gliſter, which made the Grinning Chaireman look like a Gould-fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der when diving into the bottome of his office he comes up again with his prey in his teeth, Jn a word, leaving theſe ſpirituall Fathers conſulting with the fleſh <hi>I</hi> unlock'd the ſtreet doore, ſhut it againe, went ſpeedily to my lodging, and as ſuddenly to bed, yet not till <hi>I</hi> had ſcribled down a few notes, as helps to facilitate the next dayes labour, and becauſe <hi>I</hi> reputed it an unpardonable Error to betray the leaſt dram of ſo deſerving a paſſage to unthankfull forgetful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
